ILAN STRAUSS

New York, Brooklyn, 11211 Email: ilanstrauss@newschool.edu

South African (birth), European Union (Lithuania ancestry)

Birthday: 1985

RESEARCH EXPERTISE

Firm-level data, Quantitative analysis in R, Macroeconomic Policy, International Development Economics, Financial Economics, Foreign Direct Investment, Panel Econometrics (Bayesian).

CURRENT APPOINTMENTS

Chief Consultant, Macroeconomic Policy Frameworks, African Union Commission

and International Labour Organisation (ILO), with Wits University

10/2019-12/2019

Lecturer, Rice University (Texas), Online MBA, Macroeconomics

01/2019-Present

Adjunct Lecturer, New York University (NYU), 'Intro to Macroeconomics'

06/2015-Present

Associate Research Consultant, IEJ, University of the Witwatersrand (South Africa) 01/2012—Present Write policy inputs for debate and legislative consideration by government, business, and labour on issues of minimum wages, taxes, inward and outward capital controls and flows, public debt, and other policy issues.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Economics, The New School for Social Research, New York

08/2014-03/2020 (Expected)

- Columbia University Coursework: Bayesian Statistics, Maroeconomics, Dynamical Systems

MSc, International Development Economics (First Class), SOAS, University of London

2010-2011

BSc (with Honours), Economics and History (First Class), University of Cape Town

2005-2007

Other Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant, 'Graduate Econometrics', The New School for Social Research

01/2017-05/2018

Lecturer, 'Graduate Econometrics', University of the Witwatersrand (South Africa)

01/2012 - 05/2012

OTHER PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Expert Consultant, <u>UNCTAD</u>, World Investment Reports, <u>Sample Report Here</u> 01/2014–2018

I wrote the Africa Trends section of the World Investment Report, and contributed to the Global Investment Monitor.

Research Consultant, Johns Hopkins University and the Delma Institute, Report Here 06/2016–10/2016

Coordinating Committee, National Minimum Wage Research Initiative, South Africa 09/2015-01/2017

Expert Consultant, $\underline{\text{ILO}}$, Multinational Enterprises Unit

06/2015 - 09/2015

Research Economist, African Development Bank, Tunisia – Full-Time 06/2013–06/2014

Second in command in managing the team which wrote the African Development Report, including external consultants. Write key chapters on trade, regional integration, value chains, and foreign direct investment.

Research Consultant, <u>UNECA</u>

01/2013 - 06/2013

Faculty Member, University of the Witwatersrand (South Africa), CSID – Full-Time

01/2012-12/2012

JOURNAL ARTICLES

Citations: Here

Strauss, I. 'Understanding South Africa's Current Account Deficit: the role of foreign direct investment income', *Transnational Corporations* (UNCTAD), Volume 23, Number 2, 2017.

Strauss, Ilan and Charaf-Eddine, Naym. 'Ten Commandments of Applied Regional Integration Analysis: The African Case', *African Development Review*, Special Edition, Volume 26, Issue S1, pages 7–20, November 2014.

Strauss, I. 'Manufacturing and the National Development Plan: Which way forward?', Social Dynamics: A journal of African studies, 2013, 39:1, 119–129.

BOOK CHAPTERS

Strauss, I. 'Trends in International Investment and the Activities of Multinational Enterprises', in Lisa Sachs and Lise Johnson (eds). Yearbook on International Investment Law and Policy 2019. Oxford University Press. Forthcoming 2020.

Strauss, I. 'Explaining Global Trends in FDI in 2015 and Beyond', in Lisa Sachs and Lise Johnson (eds). Yearbook on International Investment Law and Policy 2015-2016. Oxford University Press. November 2017.

Strauss, I. 'Teacher Absentee Rates: Setting the Record Straight', in Joshua Maserow(ed). *Taking Equal Education into the Classroom*. Equal Education. 2016.

Strauss, I. 'Globalisation and Taxation: Trends and Consequences', in Pons-Vignon, N and Nkosi, M (eds). Struggle in a Time of Crisis. Pluto Press. 2015.

Working Papers and Briefs

'The Global Investment Slowdown: Corporate Secular Stagnation and the Draining of the Cash Flow Swamp', with Jang-Ho Yang, INET Oxford Working Paper No. 2019-16, December 2019.

'The Global Investment Slowdown: Corporate Secular Stagnation and the Draining of the Cash Flow Swamp', with Jang-Ho Yang, Oxford Martin School Working Paper, December 2019.

Strauss, I., Isaacs, G., and Capaldo, J. 'The Impact of Minimum Wage Increases on the South African Economy in the Global Policy Model', *ILO Research Paper No. 20*, October 2017. International Labour Office.

Strauss, I. and Mavroedi, V. 'How India can Benefit from FDI: lessons from China', *Columbia FDI Perspectives*, No. 194 February 27, 2017. Columbia University.

Strauss, I. 'Understanding South Africa's Current Account Deficit: the role of FDI income', *Africa Economic Brief*, Volume 6, Issue 4, 2015, African Development Bank.

Krüger, R., and Strauss, I. 'Africa Rising Out of Itself: the growth of intra-African FDI', *Columbia FDI Perspectives*, N.139, January 19 2015, Columbia University.

Strauss, I., Johnson, L., Toledano, P., James, S. 'Background Paper on Investment Incentives: The good, the bad and the ugly: Assessing the costs, benefits and options for policy reform'. *Draft Conference Paper*. Columbia University and the IFC. 2014

Strauss, I. 'Race-to-the-bottom Labour Policies a Dead-End: the clothing and textile workers debate', South African Labour Bulletin, Vol 37 Number 1, March/April 2013.

Strauss, I. 'NDP: A Mixed bag', South African Labour Bulletin, Vol 36 Number 5, December 2012/January 2013.

Strauss, I. and Reddy, N. 'Treasury Evidence on Youth Wage Subsidy Suspect', *South African Labour Bulletin*, Vol 36 Number 3: 45-48, August/September, 2012.

Business Paper Op-Eds

Strauss, I. 'Current accounts: it's not as simple as "wine for cloth" anymore'. Financial Times, Letter to the Editor. August 27 2018.

Strauss, I. 'How a minimum wage can help South Africa". Fin 24. 02 August 2016.

Strauss, I. 'Subsidies won't make a dent'. Mail & Guardian Business Section. 07 June 2013.

Strauss, I. 'Beggar-my-neighbour' wage policies a race to the bottom'. Business Day. 12 February 2013.

Strauss, I. "Cheap labour" fiction will hobble plan's effectiveness'. Business Day. 23 January 2013

Conference Papers

Molinari, A., Strauss, I., and J. De Angelis. 'South-South cooperation between Latin America and Africa Analysis with trade and FDI indicators'. *Flacso-ISA Joint International Conference*, July 23rd-25th 2014, Buenos Aires.

Strauss, I and Charaf-Eddine, N. 'The 10 Rules of Regional Integration', *African Economic Conference* hosted by the AfDB, UNDP, and UNECA. October 28-30 2013, Johannesburg.

References

Dr. Gilad Isaacs

Co-Director, IEJ University of the Witwatersrand 62 Juta St, Johannesburg, 2000, South Africa +27 10 007 2136 gilad.isaacs@iej.org.za

Prof. Duncan Foley

Professor of Economics The New School for Social Research 6 East 16th Street New York, 10003 +1 212 229 5717 foleyd@newschool.edu

Prof. Pierre Lacour

Head, Economics Department
Division of Applied Undergraduate Studies,New
York University
7 East 12th Street
+1 212 998 7100
pierre.lacour@nyu.edu

Lisa E. Sachs

Director, Columbia Centre on Sustainable Investment (CCSI)
Columbia University, William C. Warren Hall
410 West 116th Street New York,10027
+1 212 854 1830
|sachs1@law.columbia.edu

Mr. Astrit Sulstarova

Chief, Investment Trends and Data Section UNC-TAD
Palais des Nations
CH-1211 Geneva 10, Switzerland
astrit.sulstarova@unctad.org

Dr. Barbara Ostdiek

Deputy Dean, Jones Business School Rice University 1900 Rice Boulevard, Houston, TX 77005 ostdiek@rice.edu

Last updated: January 8, 2020